All right, I am back. I know it's been a
while and but I saw something that just
captivated me and just gave me that urge
to learn something quickly. And this
time, I've seen videos of people
lighting matches with just their hands.
Not using the strip on the box, not
rubbing it off a table or anything like
that. Just their nail and the match and
boom, you've got fire. I had no idea
this was actually possible and I
wouldn't have believed it unless I'd
seen multiple videos of people doing it.
But it seems like the ultimate party
trick to be able to do this. You're like
a pyromancer just creating fire with
your bare hands. From the videos, it
doesn't even look that difficult. It
just looks like a little bit of
technique and it's something I have to
learn. So, as always, this is day one
hour zero.
It's been a while since I said that.
Basically, it looks like they're using
their thumbnail and they're [music] just
pinging the match and it just sparks and
goes. I've also seen a guy on YouTube
who does it with his teeth like that.
Yeah.
Like that.
But essentially, my understanding is if
you can generate enough friction with
just your fingernail, these can actually
go. So, I got two different boxes of
matches.
Uh one is like the little regular short
matches and one are these massive long
ones.
I Naively, I think the longer ones will
be easier to work with just because
they're longer.
But I don't think there's much more to
it than to just try and just see if I
can do it straight away.
When the video, the guy was just like
hanging down
and it was just going.
>> [snorts]
>> Holding it with the other hand.
It's not just like breaking apart.
Ow.
This is just wrecking my fingernails.
Sometimes the match like goes under your
nail and hits that like soft nail bed
bit and it's
sore.
Ow.
Ah, they keep breaking.
There's
absolutely nothing happening here.
Like there's not even a spark or smoke
or anything.
>> [music]
>> Broken.
Broken.
>> [music]
>> Even these big ones are breaking now.
[music]
>> Ah, god's sake.
>> [music]
>> Ow.
What happens is the match goes under the
nail like that and it's really really
[music]
really really really sore, especially if
you do it a thousand times in a row.
Okay, I think I have learned something
although this endeavor has been entirely
fruitless. The problem is I just keep
breaking matches. So,
here's the trick is to hold the match
like
really far down in your hand to the
point where the tip is almost touching
the skin of your fingers you can get a
really good go at it
without it breaking. I think this is
good. The problem is is it takes a
little bit of thumb dexterity to get
there and if it does actually work
the hot bit is going to be right on my
skin. So, I'm going to have to be like
really quick to get it out.
Still nothing at all, not even [music] a
spark.
Oh!
Well, that was the worst one yet.
I think I'm going [music] to have to
take
a week off or so and grow this back cuz
it's too sore.
Okay.
After a long painful journey, I have
decided that these kinds of matches, the
standard safety matches sold in the UK,
it's impossible to do this trick on
these matches. Like I have tried and
tried and tried and I am just not
getting anywhere like no
no spark or smoke or anything. I did
actually notice that my matches don't
look the same as the other people's
matches on the video. There's like two
colors on there. So, they have like a
little tip with something. So, I did
some research
and some investing
and I got a pack
of these.
>> [music]
[music]
>> This is potentially the most expensive
[music] box of matches in the world
because they don't sell these in Europe
or the UK. I think that's because we
have laws to prevent fires.
Because there's an alarming number of
warnings on this. Do not drop. Do not
mishandle. Close box before striking.
Keep away from children. The match tip
in this product contain contains
perchlorate materials. Special handling
may apply in California. To get this box
matches shipped to United Kingdom
including the box cost £50.
That's expensive. However, they are the
two-tone with the white tip matches that
I've been looking for. These must be a
bit bit more volatile. So, on the table
Yes. Okay. So, they light like just
rubbing them on the table.
So, I think we're onto something here.
I've been using the wrong matches.
In that case, here we go. Is it going to
go
with the new match?
Oh god.
Ah, still nothing.
This is impossible.
Ow.
These
These are definitely the right kind of
matches, but they are way more brittle
than these matches here.
Okay, this endeavor is completely
trashing my nails. So, I've had a wee
while off and they've grown back nicely.
And I remember when I was playing
guitar, I would get split nails and I
was always told that filing your nails
makes them stronger.
Well, I hate that sound. Then if you cut
your nails.
And then I have one more secret weapon
up my sleeve. Look at this. So, this
isn't just any superglue. This is
superglue that comes with like a little
brush.
Whilst I'm learning, I'm going to put
this superglue on and hopefully that
will stop the splits going further down.
This could be a terrible idea, but it's
got to be stronger than like regular
nail hardener, which I've never found
works at all. I think I did a pretty
good job there. Look, that's not bad.
Hopefully that stops them breaking a
bit.
Yeah, another brand of matches to try. I
don't have much hope.
>> [clears throat]
[music]
it's just impossible.
>> [music]
>> It's just impossible.
>> So, for the longest time I have been
flicking down. Like I've been putting my
nail on the match and pinging straight
down like that. But I I'm going to I
think that it's like a you actually
mimic the striking motion and actually
run your nail across the match like
that. So, across.
Oh.
You can like hear a little spark
sometimes.
What?
You hear that? See that little See that
tiny little black mark there? I'm sure
that was a spark. There's a A black mark
there. That was actually a spark.
Oh, look. I can smell it.
You [snorts] could see smoke that time.
Yeah, I can actually smell it. This is
the one.
>> [laughter]
>> Oh my god, I did it. Oh my god.
Right, so it's a
it's a
Oh, [snorts] it smells amazing. I love
the smell of matches. It's a It's a a
cross motion. It's It's not a It's not a
down motion. Let's see if we can do it
twice in a row.
Yes, that's two. That's two.
>> [laughter]
>> I got it. Right, three for three. This
really is one of those skills that like
once you get it,
it's just like you've got it every time.
And I've just cracked it. Whatever the
movement is, I've got it.
It's so satisfying and dangerous.
Right,
>> [music]
>> here's the montage.
[music]
>> All right, here's a problem for you to
solve. If you're like me, you'll enjoy
this kind of thing, okay? So,
>> [music]
>> which of these gears will rotate in the
same direction as the yellow gear? Have
a think about it. It's simpler than you
think. Pause the video if you need to.
Yep, the answers are these ones here.
So, this interactive style of
problem-solving is exactly why I love
this week's sponsor, Brilliant. I really
struggle with traditional lecture-style
learning that you do in university, you
know, where you sit in a lecture hall
and do this one-way passive learning.
And I always felt like perhaps I was a
little bit dim in that regard. But,
that's not the case at all. I'm just a
very visual, interactive learner. I like
to see what I'm working with and
problem-solve in my own [music] time in
an interactive way. And that's exactly
what Brilliant offers. It helps you
excel in maths, computer science, coding
and AI, data analysis, and science and
engineering. Whether you're honing your
skills for work or university or school,
or you just want to stay sharp and
you're curious like me, Brilliant has
you covered. The courses are designed by
world-class teachers from the likes of
Harvard, MIT, and Stanford, and they're
suitable from ages 10 to 110. My
favorite are actually the coding
courses. You guys know I'm a Python guy,
and I love this
>> [music]
>> interactive coding environment. You can
actually see how this loop actually
works. I'll show you where it is.
>> [music]
>> Um but, the best learning occurs when
you actually get things wrong, and
that's something you can't do if you're
just learning passively in a lecture
hall [music] or watching a video.
Brilliant shows you which part is
incorrect and lets you problem-solve
your way through it with guidance
>> [music]
>> when you need it. So, if you want to
learn something new or just sharpen up
the spring and summer, go check out
Brilliant. You can learn for free on
Brilliant for a full 30 days. Just go to
brilliant.org/mikeboyd
or you can scan the QR code on screen
somewhere here or there's a link in the
description. And Brilliant also give my
viewers 20% off an annual premium
subscription. And that subscription
gives you unlimited daily access to
every single [music] course on
Brilliant. Thank you very much to
Brilliant for supporting the show and
thanks to you for watching. I'll see you
all next time.
>> [music]
>> Peace.